Welcome back to AM Northwest. When it
comes to donating stuff to charity,
our next guest says most
people underestimate its value.
Here to tell us how to maximize our donations,
we welcome back antique appraiser Gary Germer.
Hi, Gary.
Hey, Helen. How you doing?
Good. So you're saying that the average person
kind of really doesn't take what they're owed.
You know, I see this a lot. I help with
downsizing. I help with other types of donations as
well.
And people, for example, I hear them say, oh,
we just took all the clothing and we dumped it
off and didn't keep track of it.
It didn't really matter. And the
fact is, is if you, it's real simple.
All you have to do is count how many shirts, how
many pants, how many, whatever you've donated,
keep track of it.
Shoot a couple of pictures of it. With the cloud
and stuff, it's easy to keep track of all that.
And then if you are the lucky one to ever get
audited, you have proof to back up why you are
claiming what you did.
Okay.
So same thing with books. You know,
this whole, since the shutdown with the,
because of the pandemic,
we did the Marie Kondo at our house
and got rid of all kinds of stuff.
Yeah. All right. But first,
let's start with clothes.
Let's talk about what are things that
would be worth a little bit more.
And I'm going to guess
designer labels are big.
Yeah. I mean, your everyday
clothes, if you go on,
Goodwill, for example, has a good website.
They have where you can get a list of what
they, what they tell the IRS your stuff's worth.
Oh, I didn't know that.
Yeah. And, and there, there's a, just
Google, just Google Goodwill is a good place.
And the IRS isn't going to argue with
those prices for your everyday stuff.
They have the really, really nice stuff.
You have designer clothes or whatever.
You want to take more for that, but you,
again, you just need to document it.
So talk, you can go on, on websites
to see what things are selling for,
like Etsy or whatever.
Right.
You can also check with a local consignment
or a local vintage clothing dealer.
They'll be glad to share information
with you on what they think it can bring.
So asking somebody who is kind of in that
field, what things are kind of going for you.
If you do your homework, due diligence,
it isn't that much work you have to do.
And you can really maximize
and just count everything.
We got rid of a bunch of books.
I sorted through all my books, which I tend to
collect like, like the dust bunnies under my
bed.
And I ended up donating
150 books, 155 books.
And you figure one to $2 a piece,
you know, that's a 200, that adds up.
Donation.
Yeah.
There's a bunch of books that
we're just collecting dust.
I'm not going to reread them again.
Yeah.
And again, you mentioned
taking pictures of them.
So you have kind of a record to
show just in case you need to.
Yeah.
You don't have to keep every title and all, but
just to prove, yeah, these are what I gave away.
Talk about more valuable things
other than clothes and books.
This is where.
If you're going to give something
valuable, the magic number is $5,000.
If you're giving an item or a collection
or an estate that's over $5,000,
you need to have a professional appraisal.
Okay.
You need to get a qualified appraiser to do whatever,
you know, for whatever fields you're giving.
If it's under $5,000, you're claiming
less than $5,000, you can do it yourself.
But again, document it.
If case the IRS does want to find out,
well, why did you just take $4,000?
Well, you know, if you're giving $5,000
for that silk flower arrangement,
you got to explain that, you know, it was from
Jesus's funeral or something to prove that it
was worth $4,000.
So are there any, are there any rules
regarding donating to a charity?
Like, do they need to use the item in the course
of their charity work or can they sell it at
an auction?
That kind of thing?
Well, when you give,
that's a good question.
Because if you give something to a
charity, something of value to the charity.
And they sell it within three years.
Technically, they're supposed to
tell the IRS what they sold it for.
And the IRS can readjust your taxes
according to what they sold it for.
So example, I had a client who donated a sofa
that I explained to him was worth an easy $2,000
for this designer sofa.
And they donated it to a charity and
they ended up selling it for $150.
And that came back to bite the donor.
Oh, wow.
And so you, ideally, you
want to give it to a charity.
You want to give it to someone
who is going to use it.
So you have art, maybe to the museum, maybe to
a retirement community or a school or someplace
where they're going to use it.
Or at least hold it for about three years.
And so that's something, if you're donating a lot
of stuff or a collection or something of value,
you really need to kind of track where it's
going to go and make sure it's not going to come
haunt you again.
Give me some examples.
I know you had a client
who donated her earrings.
Oh, yeah.
Giving to, they can sell.
They can sell the stuff.
And I had a client who donated some jewelry
and included a pair of diamond earrings,
which we felt that on a secondary
market would sell for about $1,500.
And they wanted to use
it in a charity auction.
Sure.
Jewelry is a tough thing to sell at a charity
auction because you've got 500 people in a crowd
and you're holding a
pair of diamond earrings.
Right.
You're looking at.
So what they did was a raffle.
And they sold, I suggested
let's do a raffle on them.
And they did.
And they sold.
They sold 50 tickets at $50 each and
made $2,500 on a $1,500 pair of earrings.
And it raised $2,500 for the charity.
So the client could actually take a $2,500 tax
deduction because that's what they brought.
And when it comes to donating anything, I mean,
you really want to make sure it's in good shape.
Right.
It's not broken.
You don't want any because that causes more problems
for the charity than it does solve solutions.
The biggest, the biggest expense
that most charities have.
Yeah.
That have thrift stores and such
is getting rid of people's garbage.
Right.
They come and they just
drop off their broken stuff.
So let's use a good conscience on that.
Don't give away broken stuff.
And then also to keep in mind when you're vetting
your charities, with the way things are today
and the way things can sell and be dealt with
on the internet, you can donate to any 501c3,
which is an appropriate charity.
Right.
Anything.
But deal with them on how they're going to use
it, either use it themselves if they are going
to sell it.
Right.
Make sure they have somebody who can sell
it for them and bring the maximum for it.
And then finally, I think people
don't think about this legacy giving.
You know, you think when you're filling out your
will and whatnot, you think about your major
assets.
But you can leave your entire estate.
We've handled things like that for people.
They just said we want the entire estate.
Then an estate sales run and all
the money can go to a charity.
And that's another way a nonprofit can benefit
from the stuff you or your family don't want.
Yeah.
All good points.
We'll put the information on our website.
K2.com.
Gary, thank you.
Yeah.
Good to see you.
Good to see you, too.
Thanks for having me.
You bet.